As of July of 2013, one and a half
million new Android devices were being activated every day.
So it's hard to believe that just a few
years ago, I started all meetings with potential developers explaining
what Android was and convincing them that it was
worth their time and effort developing for the platform.
It wasn't until 2010 that we even shared numbers
to indicate the growth of the platform, 100,000 daily activations
in May of that year. Which quickly grew to
500,000 in mid-2011 and crossed the million daily activations mark
in 2012. That represents over a billion Android devices around
the world, which is why I don't start my presentations
asking if anyone in the room has an Android device
anymore. To me though, the biggest surprise in those early
days was how much effort was required to convince people
that developing for mobile at all was a worthwhile investment.
A huge number of people use their phones to go
online and many of them use their phone as the main
way to do so. One study by the Pew Research
Internet Project in 2013 found that nearly two-thirds of mobile owners
use their phones to go online, double the rate found
in 2009. And that a third of phone users use mostly
their phone to get online. Think about that for a second.
These portable phones have become pocket computers constantly connected to the
cloud to make the sum of human knowledge available
to us at a touch and a glance. It's no
wonder then that for a growing number of people,
mobile isn't how to get online when you're away from
your desk. It's actually displacing PCs as their primary
computing platform. The change is so dramatic and the trend
so clear that companies like Google, who depend entirely on
the internet, have a mobile first policy, ensuring that the
mobile experience is the first consideration when building
new products. This trend is particularly evident amongst younger
users who grew up using mobiles and especially
in emerging markets like Africa and Asia, where the
infrastructure to support ubiquitous broadband for desktops isn't
as readily available. I saw this firsthand when I
had the good fortune to visit Kenya a
few years ago. Ubiquitous phones and passionate, talented developers
weren't really familiar, but what really struck me was the degree
to which mobile phones had become an integral part of people's
everyday lives. It wasn't just checking email and posting to Facebook,
it was using [UNKNOWN] to buy everything from groceries to bus
fare. Mobiles was such a part of life that I heard
rather than buying someone a drink to show that you're interested,
you'd send them a phone credit so that they can call
you if they felt the same way. In the transition of
smartphones from tech accessory to a part of life to the
main way you get online to how you pay for things,
even how you flirt, represents a huge opportunity for us as
developers. The question is, how are you going to change the world?